Guide to the Brooks Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Brooks family papers
1866-2010
MS 1784
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
48
(114 boxes)
The Brooks Family Papers contain materials relating to Harold Allen Brooks, Sr., Mildred McNeill-Brooks, and their son, Harold Allen Brooks, Jr. The materials consist of correspondence, writings, financial documents, photographs, and research files. The latter contains materials regarding Frank Lloyd Wright, other Prairie School architects, and Charles-Edouard Jeanneret. The research files on Jeanneret bring together documents and photographs collected from around the world and provide comprehensive documentation of Jeanneret's personal life, influences, and architectural career. There is a presentation drawing by Euston made after the architect's first visit to the site in the spring of 1939 and a writing by H. Allen Brooks as to why he became an architectural historian as it relates to the presentation drawing.
Brooks family
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of H. Allen Brooks, 2000, 2004, 2006, and 2010.
Related Material
Woodruff Family Papers, MS 1143. Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library
Arrangement
Arranged in four series and two additions: I. Mildred McNeill-Brooks, 1866-1990. II. Harold Allen Brooks, Sr., 1893-1950. III. Harold Allen Brooks, Jr. Personal, Correspondence, and Writings, 1925-2002. IV. Harold Allen Brooks, Jr. Research, 1899-2001.
Biographical / Historical
Harold Allen Brooks, Sr. was born in New Haven, Connecticut, in 1886. He served in the army during World War I and afterwards became a banker. In June 1923, he married Mildred McNeill. McNeill was born in Brooklyn, New York, in 1895. She attended Vassar College and was a nurse with the YWCA before marrying Brooks. Both died in the early 1950s.
Harold Allen Brooks, Jr. was born in 1925. Brooks, Jr., received degrees from Dartmouth College (B.A., 1950), Yale University (M.A., 1955), and Northwestern University (Ph.D., 1957). He served in the United States Army. For most of his professional career, Brooks, Jr. taught architectural history at the University of Toronto. He specialized in Frank Lloyd Wright and the Prairie School and Charles-Edouard Jeanneret, commonly known as Le Corbusier. Brooks, Jr. publications include The Prairie School: Frank Lloyd Wright and his Midwest Contemporaries and Le Corbusier's Formative Years. He also edited the thirty-two volume Le Corbusier Archive and served as president of the Society of Architectural Historians. In 1986, Brooks, Jr. became professor emeritus of architecture at the University of Toronto. He died on August 8, 2010, in Hanover, New Hampshire.
Scope and Contents
The Brooks Family Papers contain materials relating to Harold Allen Brooks, Sr., Mildred McNeill-Brooks, and their son, Harold Allen Brooks, Jr. The materials consist of correspondence, writings, financial documents, photographs, and research files. The latter contains materials regarding Frank Lloyd Wright, other Prairie School architects, and Charles-Edouard Jeanneret. The research files on Jeanneret bring together documents and photographs collected from around the world and provide comprehensive documentation of Jeanneret's personal life, influences, and architectural career. There is a presentation drawing by Euston made after the architect's first visit to the site in the spring of 1939 and a writing by H. Allen Brooks as to why he became an architectural historian as it relates to the presentation drawing.
Prairie school (Architecture); La Chaux-de-Fonds (Switzerland) -- Buildings, structures, etc.; New Haven (Conn.) -- History; Le Corbusier, 1887-1965; Brooks, H. Allen (Harold Allen), 1925-2010; Wright, Frank Lloyd, 1867-1959; Brooks family
- Mildred McNeill-Brooks, 1866-1990; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains personal papers of Mildred McNeill-Brooks. Correspondence has been left in original envelopes and is arranged chronologically. Diaries, also arranged chronologically, document the daily life of McNeill-Brooks from the age of 14 until her death in 1951. Subjects discussed include travel abroad, foreign cultures, social events with friends, married life, and on occasion, national and international events. The Albums, Scrapbook, and Yearbooks provide photographic material and personal information about McNeill-Brooks and her ancestors. Many of the Photographs are identified and some include dates. Drawings of Connecticut landscapes are often signed by McNeill-Brooks
  - Correspondence, 1916-1944, undated (Box 1–2)
  - Diaries
    - 1910-1925 [6 folders] (Box 3)
    - 1926-1951 [5 folders] (Box 4)
  - Albums
    - Baby photograph album with telegrams, 1895 (Box 5)
    - Baby/childhood book [including birth announcement telegrams], 1895-1907 (Box 5)
    - Photograph album, 1904-1912 (Box 5)
    - Vassar photograph album, Circa 1914-1918 (Box 5)
    - Wedding gift album, 1923 (Box 5)
  - Scrapbook [4 folders], Circa 1866-1951 (Box 6)
  - Yearbooks
    - High school [3 folders], 1911-1914 (Box 6)
    - Vassar, 1915 (Box 7)
  - Car insurance policy, driver's license, 1918, 1919 (Box 7)
  - War department letters, certificates, 1919, 1920 (Box 7)
  - "National League for Women's Service Automobile Section" certificate, 1917 (Box 7)
  - New Testament, Vassar College catalogue, 1871, 1914-1915 (Box 7)
  - Ephemera, letters, papers, coins, 1932, 1945, 1990, undated (Box 7)
  - Photographs [14 folders], 1920-1950, undated (Box 7–8)
  - Drawings, 1939-1940 (Box 8)
  - High school diplomas, 1908-1914 (Box 9)
  - World War I YWCA nursing certificate, 1917 (Box 9)
  - Dividend ledgers, 1932-1934 (Box 9)
- Harold Allen Brooks, Sr., 1893-1950; Series II
  The materials in this series mostly consist of financial documents including bank statements, checks, receipts, and stock certificates. There is a limited amount of personal materials and correspondence. One folder documents Brooks's service in World War I. A large album of unidentified photographs, probably from the mid-nineteenth century, is included in the series, as well as an additional folder of photographs.
  - Personal, 1902, 1916, 1922-1925, 1948, undated (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, 1914-1925, undated (Box 10)
  - Financial
    - General [9 folders], 1893-1925, undated (Box 10)
    - Bank statements [2 folders], 1924-1925 (Box 10)
  - World War I, 1918-1919, undated (Box 11)
  - Photographs [mostly unidentified], 1922-1923, 1950, undated (Box 12–13)
- Harold Allen Brooks, Jr. Personal, Correspondence, and Writings, 1925-2010; Series III
  The series is comprised of non-research materials of Harold Allen Brooks, Jr. Personal papers are arranged topically and contain biographical information. The majority consist of photographs and slides that have been left in their original containers with Brooks's identification. The photographs document Brooks's personal life from childhood through retirement. Correspondence is subdivided into personal and professional correspondence, following Brooks's own arrangement. Professional correspondence is primarily arranged chronologically, but includes topically arranged files. Personal correspondence is arranged chronologically and is mainly dated to the 1940s and after 1980. The former has been left in original envelopes and is largely outgoing correspondence to Brooks's parents. Short Writings and Books files comprise the majority of the Writings section. Short Writings include handwritten and typed manuscripts. It is unclear whether they were published.
  - Personal
    - General [includes diplomas], 1925-2000, undated (Box 14)
    - General [includes diplomas; 4 folders], 1925-2000, undated (Box 15)
    - Biographical, 1979-2010, undated (Box 15)
    - Baby book, 1925-1926 (Box 15)
    - Class books, 1941 (Box 15)
    - Clippings, 1964-1998, undated (Box 15)
    - Financial, 1952-1985 (Box 15)
    - Passports, 1958-1997 (Box 16)
    - Teaching materials [2 folders], 1958-1985 (Box 16)
    - Travel [2 folders], 1986-1987, 1997-1998 (Box 16)
    - Photographs
      - Loose [mostly positives, includes some slides; one folder of negatives, box 17; one folder of drawings, box 18], Circa 1925-2000, undated (Box 17–22)
      - Albums
        - "Join the Army and See the World", 1946-1947 (Box 23)
        - "Join the Army..." [loose materials], 1946-1947, undated (Box 23)
        - Miniature photograph album, Undated (Box 23)
        - "Photographs by Allen Brooks" [2 albums], 1934-1938, undated (Box 23)
        - "Round Hill and", 1939-1942 (Box 23)
        - "Round Hill and" [loose materials; 2 folders], 1930-1954, undated (Box 23)
      - Slides, 1946-ca. 1990, undated (Box 24–28)
  - Correspondence
    - Professional
      - Chronological
        - 1976-1986 [11 folders] (Box 29)
        - 1987-1989 [8 folders] (Box 30)
        - 1990-1997 [8 folders] (Box 31)
        - 1998-1999, no date [3 folders] (Box 32)
      - Topical
        - Administrative, 1977-1981 (Box 32)
        - Arts and Humanities Foundation [includes administrative records], 1963-1966 (Box 32)
        - George Braziller, Inc. [includes administrative records], 1983-1984 (Box 32)
        - Grants, 1962-1974 (Box 32)
        - Jeanneret, Charles-Edouard [information request letters], 1975-1995 (Box 32)
        - Massachusetts Institute of Technology Press [includes administrative records], 1980-1982 (Box 32)
        - Prairie school [information request letters], 1972-1983 (Box 32)
        - Publications, 1959-1965 (Box 33)
        - Society of Architectural Historians [includes administrative records; 9 folders], 1962-1973 (Box 33)
        - Writings on Wright, 1970-1973 (Box 34)
        - University of Chicago Press, 1994-2000 (Box 34)
    - Personal
      - 1939-1946 [letters in envelopes] (Box 35)
      - 1947-1955 [letters in envelopes] (Box 36)
      - 1960-1991 [9 folders] (Box 37)
      - 1992-2000 [8 folders] (Box 38)
  - Writings
    - Journal of cross-country trip [in form of a series of letters to his parents], 1947 (Box 39)
    - Graduate school papers [includes photographs and notes relating to Yale masters thesis on Leonard Eidlitz; 2 folders], 1953-1956 (Box 39)
    - Short writings [includes articles and lectures]
      - 1958-1965 [4 folders] (Box 39)
      - 1965-1969 [6 folders] (Box 40)
      - 1970-1986 [8 folders] (Box 41)
      - 1987-2000, no date [6 folders] (Box 42)
      - Audio materials
        Conditions Governing Access
        Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
        - 4 lectures on Jeanneret, 1978 February; 2 (Box 43–44)
        - "F. L. W.: The Destruction of the Box", 1978 February; 1 (Box 45)
    - Books
      - Le Corbusier [edited by Brooks], 1987 (Box 46)
      - Le Corbusier's Formative Years [by Brooks]
        - Printed copy, 1997 (Box 46)
        - Manuscript [14 folders], 1977-1998 (Box 47)
        - Reproductions used in the book [4 folders], Undated (Box 48)
      - Frank Lloyd Wright and the Prairie School [by Brooks], 1984 (Box 49)
      - Prairie School Architecture [edited and introduced by Brooks; 2 copies], 1975 (Box 49)
      - The Prairie School: Frank Lloyd Wright and His Midwest Contemporaries [by Brooks], 1972 (Box 50)
      - Writings on Wright [edited, introduced, and with commentary by Brooks], 1981 (Box 50)
    - Reviews of H. Allen Brooks, Jr.'s books [2 folders], 1972-1997 (Box 51)
    - Publicity
      - General [2 folders], 1976-2001 (Box 51)
      - Posters, 1978-2002 (Box 52)
- Harold Allen Brooks, Jr. Research, 1899-2001; Series IV
  The research files of Harold Allen Brooks, Jr. consist of notes, correspondence, printed materials, photographs, and photocopies of original documents. The series is divided into two sections: Prairie School/Frank Lloyd Wright and Charles-Edouard Jeanneret (Le Corbusier).
  The Prairie School materials are arranged topically with folder headings derived largely from Brooks's own titles. A large number of photographs, mostly identified and mainly used in Brooks's book, The Prairie School: Frank Lloyd Wright and his Midwest Contemporaries, are a substantial part of the series. Prairie School also contains drawings and blueprints of the buildings of Prairie School architects.
  The arrangement of the research files on Jeanneret corresponds to Brooks'sbook, Le Corbusier's Formative Years. Wherever possible, the integrity of Brooks's ordering and folder titles has been maintained. A large amount of the Jeanneret material consists of photocopies of original handwritten correspondence, writings, and drawings, collected from around the world. Much of this material was later transcribed and where transcriptions exist, they follow the photocopied originals. Near the end of the series are audiotapes of interviews conducted by Brooks and others with individuals who knew Jeanneret.
  - Prairie School/Frank Lloyd Wright
    - General [includes miscellaneous photographs and plans; 11 folders], 1901-2001, undated (Box 53–54)
    - Architectural Record clippings, 1904-1907, undated (Box 55)
    - Ashbee-Wright correspondence, 1970-1973 (Box 55)
    - Bentley, P. D., 1966-1971 (Box 55, Folder 3)
    - Byrne, Barry [2 folders], 1959-1970, undated (Box 55)
    - Drummond, W. E., 1957-1968 (Box 55)
    - Garden, Hugh M. G., 1961, 1969-1970 (Box 55)
    - Griffin,W. B.
      - General, 1956-1970 (Box 55)
      - Lists of designs and drawings, undated (Box 55)
      - "Walter Burley Griffin in His Own Right", 1998; 1 (Box 56)
    - Maher, G. W.
      - General, 1957-1966 (Box 57)
      - "Residences by G. W. Maher", undated (Box 57)
    - Outlines of England/Scotland, undated (Box 57)
    - "Papers I have delivered", 1966, 1969, undated (Box 57)
    - "The Prairie School Catalog" [by Phillip C. Pecord], 1987 (Box 57)
    - Purcell, William Gray and George Grant Elmslie
      - General, 1955-1967 (Box 57)
      - List of designs, undated (Box 57)
    - Richardson [Henry Hobson] and Wright [Frank Lloyd], 1969 (Box 57)
    - Silsbee, J. L. [2 folders], 1968-1969 (Box 57)
    - Sullivan, Francis C., 1967-1969, undated (Box 57)
    - Sullivan, Louis, 1922-1925, undated (Box 57)
    - Van Bergen, J. S., 1955-1966, 1991 (Box 57)
    - Warn, Robert, 1969 (Box 57)
    - Wright, Frank Lloyd
      - General [8 folders], 1905-1972, undated (Box 58)
      - "Restoration of Frank Lloyd Wright's Heurtley House", 2001; 1 (Box 59)
      - Notecard files [handwritten; arranged by topic], undated (Box 60)
    - Wright, Frank Lloyd and Le Corbusier: A Comparison of their Formative Years, 1981 (Box 61)
    - Wright, John Lloyd, 1971-1972 (Box 61)
    - Photographs
      - Positives [primarily of buildings and plans; many used in The Prairie School: Frank Lloyd Wright and his Midwest Contemporaries; most identified], undated (Box 62–67)
      - Negatives, 1955-1963, undated (Box 68–70)
    - Drawings
      - Byrne, Barry [includes joint projects with Walter Burley Griffin; blueprints and blue-line prints], 1914-1917 (Box 71–72)
      - Greene, C. Sumner [original drawings], undated (Box 73)
      - Griffin, Walter Burley [includes original drawings of residential buildings from Illinois and blue-line prints], 1906-1914, undated (Box 74–75)
      - Historic American Buildings Survey [black-line prints], 1963 (Box 76)
      - Lucknow University library [unidentified architect; blueprints], undated (Box 76)
      - Tallmadge, Thomas E. and Vernon S. Watson [blue-line prints with pencil annotation], undated (Box 76)
      - Van Bergen, John S. [blueprints and facsimile drawings], 1928, 1941 (Box 76)
      - Wright, Frank Lloyd [blue-line prints and scale drawings], 1964, undated (Box 77)
    - Notecard files [handwritten; alphabetically arranged by topic], undated (Box 78–79)
  - Jeanneret, Charles-Edouard [Le Corbusier]
    - La Chaux-de-Fonds, 1887-1907 [Section I from Le Corbusier's Formative Years ]
      - Jeanneret-Gris, Georges-Edouard [father; journal]
        - Photocopies of original entries, 1899-1923 (Box 80)
        - Typed transcriptions of original entries [2 folders], 1899-1923 (Box 80)
        - Excerpts, explanations, and notes, undated (Box 80)
      - Jeanneret [Charles-Edouard] 1900-1911 (thru Voyage d'Orient )
        - Article on 1914 competition design (Box 81)
        - Letterheads and signatures (Box 81)
        - Notes relating to chapter I [Childhood and Early Schooling, 1887-1902] (Box 81)
        - Diverse, 1902-1907 (Box 81)
        - Biographical materials of Jeanneret associates (Box 81)
        - 1902-1907 [Ecole d'art] (Box 81)
        - 1902-1910 (Box 81)
        - 1907-1909 (Box 81)
        - 1908-1911 [Ecole d'art] (Box 81)
        - Student papers [for a course taught by Brooks] (Box 81)
        - Paris chapter (Box 81)
        - 1910 [Swiss interlude] (Box 81)
        - 1910-1911 [Germany] (Box 81)
        - Urbanism (Box 81)
        - 1911 [Voyage d'orient] (Box 81)
        - Voyage d'orient student papers [for a course taught by Brooks] (Box 81)
        - Loose materials (Box 81)
      - Visual materials [includes photographic reproductions, images, figures, and drawings]
        - Ecole d'art (Box 82)
        - Farm Houses, 1910, post-1912 (Box 82)
        - Family & Charles-Edouard Jeanneret [includes several letters, some with sketches] (Box 82)
        - La Chaux-de-Fonds [1 folder of positives; 3 folders of unique negatives made from original blueprints] (Box 83)
        - L'Eplattenier's (Charles) architectural designs (Box 83)
        - Jeanneret's watches and clocks (Box 83)
        - Renan, La Vie de Jésus (Box 83)
        - Buildings and building projects, 1904-1911
          - Chaux-de-Fonds photographs, 1984 (Box 84)
          - Photographs, loose [includes one student paper] (Box 84)
          - Jeanneret's architectural projects, 1904-1907 (Box 84)
          - Beau site project: 1905 (Box 84)
          - Villa Fallet (Box 84)
          - Villa Stotzer (Box 84)
          - Villa Jaquemet (Box 84)
          - Les ateliers d'art réunis (Box 84)
    - Travels and Apprenticeships, 1907-1911 [Section II from Le Corbusier's Formative Years ]
      - Correspondence
        - Parents
          - Photocopies of originals
            - Outgoing [4 folders), 1907-1910 (Box 85)
            - Incoming, 1911 June-October (Box 85)
          - Typed transcriptions of originals
            - Outgoing [5 folders], 1907-1911 (Box 85)
            - Incoming [2 folders], 1911, 1918-1919 (Box 85)
        - Perret, Auguste, 1912-1916 (Box 86)
        - DuBois, Max, 1910-1912 (Box 86)
        - Postcards, 1911-1918 (Box 86)
        - L'Eplattenier, Charles [3 folders], 1907-1911 (Box 86)
        - Chapallaz, René,postcards, 1908-1909 (Box 86)
        - Germany [includes diverse German material and student papers regarding Germany from a course taught by Brooks]
          - Ritter, William, 1918-1920 (Box 87)
          - Klipstein, August [includes materials on Jeanneret trip to the Orient; 3 folders], 1911-1951 (Box 87)
          - L'Abeille: Supplément du National Suisse, 1910 May 15 (Box 87)
          - Osthaus, Karl Ernst, 1911-1913 (Box 87)
          - Student papers [for a course taught by Brooks], 1973-1985 (Box 87)
      - "La Construction des Villes" [Jeanneret manuscript]
        - Photocopies of original, 1910-1915 (Box 88)
        - Typed transcriptions of original [3 folders], 1910 (Box 88)
        - Dossier [includes notes and reproductions of images and drawings], undated (Box 88)
        - Student papers [for a course taught by Brooks], 1976 (Box 88)
      - Jeanneret sketchbooks [includes research on the sketchbooks; 8 folders], 1908-1916 (Box 89)
      - Photographs
        - Swiss travels, undated (Box 90)
        - Italian trip, 1907, 1911 (Box 90)
        - Vienna, 1907-1908 (Box 90)
        - Nuremberg, 1908 March (Box 90)
        - "La Saulot" chez Perret, 1908-1909 (Box 90)
        - "Perret Project:" La "Maison Bouteille", Circa 1908-1909 (Box 90)
        - Paris [chez Perret], 1908-1909 (Box 90)
        - Paris sketches [minus chez Perret], 1908-1909 (Box 90)
        - Germany, 1910-1911 (Box 90)
        - Prague, 1907 November (Box 90)
        - Voyage d'orient, 1911 (Box 90)
        - Loose materials, undated (Box 90)
    - Early Professional Career, 1912-1916 [Section III of Le Corbusier's Formative Years ]
      - Correspondence
        - 1913-1915
          - Photocopies of originals [2 folders] (Box 91)
          - Typed transcriptions of originals [2 folders] (Box 91)
        - Ritter, William
          - Photocopies of originals [3 folders], 1910-1918 (Box 92)
          - Typed transcriptions of originals [6 folders], 1910-1933 (Box 92)
          - Ritter to L'Eplattenier, Charles, 1907 (Box 92)
          - Sketch of Janko Cádra, 1912 August 12 (Box 92)
          - Loose materials, undated (Box 92)
      - Villa Schwob
        - General, 1918 (Box 93)
        - Correspondence, 1917-1920 (Box 93)
        - Research, undated (Box 93)
        - Student papers [for a course taught by Brooks], undated (Box 93)
      - Jeanneret, 1912-1920
        - Perrin's original drawing, 1912 (Box 94)
        - Jeanneret and Berlage article on Frank Lloyd Wright and Louis Sullivan [includes related correspondence], 1912, 1953 (Box 94)
        - Les ateliers d'art réunis, 1912-1914 (Box 94)
        - Jeanneret writings, 1912-1916 (Box 94)
        - La Chaux-de-Fonds, Le Loche, 1912-1915 (Box 95)
        - Ecole d'art [includes two student papers], 1912-1914 (Box 95)
        - Proportions-regulating lines [includes two student papers], 1912-1927, 1976, 1985 (Box 95)
        - Affaire Scala, 1916-1921, 1981 (Box 95)
        - Articles by and about Jeanneret, 1916 August-December (Box 95)
        - Ditisheim, A., E., and H., 1914-1916 (Box 95)
        - Garnier, Tony, Circa 1915 (Box 95)
        - Stewart, David, dissertation of, 1972 (Box 95)
        - Diverse materials, 1917-1920 (Box 95)
        - Après le Cubisme [publication by Jeanneret and Amédée Ozenfant], 1918 (Box 95)
        - Bulletin Thomas, 1918 November (Box 95)
        - Student papers [for a course taught by Brooks], 1976, 1982 (Box 95)
        - Diverse materials, post-1920 (Box 95)
        - Loose materials, 1914-1984 (Box 95)
      - Photographs
        - Executed work, 1912
          - General, 1912-1929, 1979 (Box 96)
          - Villa Jeanneret-Perret (Box 96)
          - Villa Jacot (Box 96)
        - Projects, 1912-1916
          - Klipstein project, 1914 (Box 97)
          - Project F, 1916 (Box 97)
          - Furniture-Ditisheim & Schwob & Jeanneret, 1912-1915, 1975-1985 (Box 97)
          - Raphy Schwob-bibliothèque, 1913, 1925 (Box 97)
          - Jeanneret's designs,Ecole d'art, 1912-1914 (Box 97)
          - Nouvelle section,Ecole d'art, 1912-1914 (Box 97)
          - Furniture: Jeanneret at Musée des Arts Décoratifs, Paris, 1979 (Box 97)
          - Paix 11, 1913 March (Box 97)
          - Arnold Beck project, 1912-1914 (Box 97)
        - Bibliothèque Nationale/"La Construction des Villes" sketches, 1915 (Box 98)
        - Dom-Ino, post-1914 (Box 98)
        - Architectural projects [except Dom-Ino], 1912-1916 (Box 98)